We have seen that DM accesses are slow
because really we have to use the row
decoder to select the row then get those
bits onto the bit lines then sense
what's on the bit lines and so on and
only then we get the values in the row
buffer from which we can read them and
send them back to the processor. But not
all of the DM accesses have to be that
slow. So we will discuss a technique
called fast page mode that makes some of
the DM accesses a lot faster than
others. Remember our organization of the
DM. We use some part of the address to
select a row. That row of bits gets
output to the sense amplifier. We then
latch those into the row buffer. And
then from the row buffer we use the
column address to select a bit to
output. And then from the row buffer the
column decoder using the column address
selects the actual bit to output. Note
that once we have done all of this the
row buffer can retain the entire row. So
if we want to read a bit from the same
row we don't need to go through the
whole row address sense amplifier
row buffer mechanism again. What we can
do is simply keep what we have in the
row buffer and just change the column
address. Then the bit simply gets read
out of the row buffer without a new DM
access. So this approach of finding what
we need in the row buffer is called fast
page mode. It's not called fast row mode
just because some people prefer to call
some people prefer to call a memory row
a page. It usually has thousands of
bits. So people call it a page. It has
nothing to do with the pages that we use
for virtual memory. It's just a name for
something that has a lot of bits in this
case. So fast page mode works this way.
We do what is called opening a page.
That's that amounts to providing a row
address, selecting a row, send
amplification of what the cells output
and latching what we get into the row
buffer. Now we can do a series of reads
and writes to the page which really
happens to the row buffer. We can read
or we can modify bits in the row buffer.
Finally, when we want to do something on
another row in memory, we do what is
called closing the page. We now use the
sense amplifiers to write back to the
row what we have in a row buffer. It
could be different data than what we
read because we have been modifying it
also in between. And this way if we want
to do a single read, we would have to
open a page, do one read, then close the
page to write back things to our memory
cells because of the destructive read.
And then finally, we have to do what is
called closing the page, which amounts
to writing the data from the row buffer
back into the row from which we read it.
So if we want to do a single memory
read, we would open a page
The data is now in the row buffer and no
longer in the row. Do the read from the
row buffer and then close the page which
causes the data to be sent back and
written back to the row. We can do a
single write which amounts to opening a
page. The data lines up in the row
buffer. We do a single write. So we
modify a bit in the row buffer and then
we close the page which causes the row
to get the new data. and some of the
bits may not have changed which is why
we had to read in the first place. But
we can do a lot more than just one
operation in between opening and closing
a page. So usually it's advantageous to
open a page, do all the reads and writes
that we can to that page before we close
the page and open another page.